Columbian Harmony and Payne Cemetery 066
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Columbian Harmony and Payne's Cemetery Ledgers Collection
1901-1959
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Harmony Cemetery (Washington, D.C.)
Payne's Cemetery (Washington, D.C.)
066
16 Linear feet
8 Boxes
Arrangement
Processed wihtout series.
Biographical / Historical
The Columbian Harmony Cemetery was established as a resting ground for free blacks in Washington, D.C. Established by the Columbian Harmony Society in 1829, the cemetery was situated between Boundary Street (present-day Florida Avenue), S Street, and 6th Street NW. In 1848, the City Council passed an ordinance prohibiting new burial grounds in the city limits. Since the cemetery continued to expand, it was relocated to land on Rhode Island Avenue and 9th Street, NE in 1858, which was outside the city limits. In 1960, due to a lack of space and neglected care, the Harmony Cemetery (including the remains) was moved to Hyattsville, Maryland and renamed the "National Harmony Memorial Park." Payne's Cemetery was established prior to 1880 in Washington, D.C. The land was located at 4724 Benning Road SE and was used primarily as a burial place for African Americans in the District. In 1961, Louis H. Bell purchased the property and attempted to disinter the remains from the cemetery. However, due to continuous neglect, many of the grave markers had been moved or destroyed. In 1969, Mr. Bell had the remains moved to the National Harmony Memorial Park in Maryland. The land that was once Payne's Cemetery is now the Fletcher-Johnson Elementary School.
Custodial History
Paul E. Sluby, Sr. donated this collection to the Library in May 2006.
Scope and Contents
The ten ledgers were organized in chronological order based on the first entry in each book. Information found in the ledgers includes: name of deceased, plot location, and date of burial.
African Americans; Cemeteries; Burial records
- Series 1
  - Columbian Harmony Ledger, July 6 1901-April 17 1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Columbian Harmony Ledger, April 16 1903-December 31 1904 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Columbian Harmony Ledger, December 30 1904-July 8 1906 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Columbian Harmony Ledger, July 10 1906-September 30 1912 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Columbian Harmony Ledger, July 1 1910-September 30 1914 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Columbian Harmony Ledger, October 1 1912-March 4 1931 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Columbian Harmony Ledger, March 25 1931-October 31 1941 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Columbian Harmony Ledger, November 3 1941-July 30 1953 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Columbian Harmony Ledger, August 25 1953-December 21 1959 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Payne Cemetery Ledger, July 20 1932-February 20 1952 (Box 8, Folder 1)